They fought south of the city, and died north of the wall.
战城南 死郭北
Left out in the wild, unburied, for the crows to peck and gnaw.
野死不葬乌可食
Tell the crows for me: eat well, feast your fill.
为我谓乌 且为客豪
Left in the wild, surely unburied— how could rotten flesh escape your beak?
野死谅不葬 腐肉安能去子逃
Well, Xiao Wuyi...
萧无衣啊 萧无衣
After all these years of war,
仗打了这么多年
you still haven't earned a good reputation.
没留下好名声啊
This family
这家人
seems to have been gone for a long time.
看起来早就不在了
Da.
阿大
Everyone is gone.
人都不见了
How am I supposed to look into this?
我该怎么查
I need to tell Wuyi about all this.
我得把这些告诉无衣
Yizhi!
易之
Wuyi.
无衣
What are you doing here?
你怎么在这儿
I was waiting for you.
我在这儿等你啊
Xiao Wuyi!
萧无衣
How did you know I was coming back to the capital today?
你怎么知道我今日回京啊
In your letter, you said you were coming back by water.
你信中说走水路回京
Counting the days, it had to be today,
算算日子也就今日
so I came here to wait for you.
专门在此等你
I heard the battle at Jiuzhang Plain was especially brutal.
听闻九丈原一战十分惨烈
How are you?
你怎么样
Let me have a look at you.
我看看你
I'm fine.
无碍
You've been traveling day and night this whole way.
你这一路风餐露宿
You must be starving.
肯定饿了吧
I brought your favorite taro pastries.
给你带了你最爱吃的芋酥
Hurry and try some.
快尝尝
You really know me.
还是兄弟懂我
I've been sick of dry rations this entire journey.
我这一路吃干粮都吃腻了
I've been saving my appetite for getting back to Jiankang.
留着肚子回剑慷呢
Watch your manners.
你注意点形象
Look at you, eating like a starving ghost.
瞧瞧你这饿死鬼的模样
How are you supposed to be the elegant Prince Qi from the rumors?
哪像传说中的翩翩公子岐王啊
That's a bad habit from back when we were on the run.
当年逃跑落下的毛病
If you eat too slowly,
吃太慢
your food gets snatched and you starve.
可是会被抢走 会饿死的
I still haven't managed to shake it.
到现在都改不掉
Yizhi,
易之
thank you for helping with the matter in Yongzhou.
雍州之事谢谢你帮忙
Wuyi,
无衣
is something wrong?
你有事
I waited here for you today
我今日特意在此等你
because I want you to stay out of the capital for now.
是想让你暂时不要回京
Something is about to happen in the capital.
京中要出事
Don't tell me it's Prince Changsha again.
该不会是长沙王
No.
不
It's me.
是我
What did you do?
你有何事啊
I'm taking a secondary consort.
我要娶侧妃
Again?
又娶
Isn't that a good thing?
这不是好事吗
I'll be your best man.
我给你当傧相
This marriage was arranged by the Empress Dowager.
这场婚礼是太后赐婚
The whole city is bound to be watching.
注定全城瞩目
And Prince Changsha has been planning for this for a long time.
而长沙王筹谋已久
There's no way he'll willingly let me marry this lady.
绝不会甘心我娶这家女郎
When the time comes,
到时候
chaos is bound to break out in the capital,
京中各方必然生乱
and bloodshed will be inevitable.
免不了一场腥风血雨
It will be safest for you to return
你等一切尘埃落定之后再回来
only after everything has settled.
最安全
Now I'm curious.
我倒是好奇了
Just which family's daughter
究竟是哪家女郎
has both you and Prince Changsha fighting to marry her?
你和长沙王都抢着要娶啊
The daughter of Grand Tutor Xie—
谢太傅之女
Xie Jiayu.
谢嘉鱼
Prince Qi is back!
岐王殿下回来了
It's been more than half a year. You finally made it back.
大半年了 你总算回来了
Master has really missed you.
老师可想你了
Come on, let's go drink now that you're back.
回来了喝酒去啊
Alright, alright.
行了行了
Master.
老师
You should all head back first.
你们先回去吧
Head back first.
先回
Master, I heard—
老师 我听说
I already know.
为师知道
I remember you once told me
我记得你曾经说过
that during the unrest in Qizhou,
当年岐州民乱
you ran into danger on your way back to the capital.
你在回京的途中遇到了危险
It was Young Master Xiao who saved you and escorted you
是萧世子救了你
and the Princess of Pingning County safely back to the capital.
并且护送你和平宁县主回京
You've known each other since then?
你们是旧相识
Yes.
是
Have you been in contact recently?
近来可有联络
It is a friendship of gentlemen.
君子之交
So in your eyes,
在你心里
Young Master Xiao is actually a gentleman?
萧世子竟然是个君子
When we were young, he once told me
年少时他同我说过
that, for the sake of protecting the realm,
为护天下
he wanted
此生
to become the greatest general under heaven.
他要做天底下最厉害的将军
But after returning to the capital,
可他回京之后
he killed court officials and intimidated the entire court.
杀朝臣 震百官
Do you still think
你觉得他还是
he's the same young man you once knew?
当年你所认识的那个少年吗
"How shall it be said that you have no clothes?
岂曰无衣
I will share my long robes with you."
与子同袍
It is his name,
是他的名
and also his aspiration.
也是他的志
Yes.
是
Perhaps when Xiao Sheng chose the name "Wuyi"—"No Clothes" — for himself,
也许当年萧晟为自己取名无衣
he truly meant those words.
是出自于真心
But power...
但权力
Power changes people.
权力是会改变一个人的
Perhaps he is no longer
也许他已经不再是你
the person you once knew.
当初所认识的那个人了
I'll go see him myself.
我去找他
I'll tell him that I like Yao Yao,
我告诉他 我心仪夭夭
and ask him to call off the marriage.
让他退了这桩婚事
The Empress Dowager herself arranged this marriage.
太后赐婚
How could it possibly be withdrawn?
岂能收回
Then I'll go beg the Empress Dowager.
那我就去求太后啊
Jiankang Palace is not somewhere you can simply barge into.
剑慷宫不是那么好闯的
I know.
我知道
Master,
老师
before I returned this time,
学生这趟回来
I prepared a betrothal gift for Yao Yao.
为夭夭备了个求亲之礼
Please help me pass it on to her.
还请老师帮忙转交
I've already made up my mind.
我已经决定了
No matter how difficult it is,
即便再困难
even if it means going into Jiankang Palace,
就算是剑慷宫
I'm willing to try.
我也愿意试试
For Yao Yao,
为了夭夭
I'd do anything.
我什么都愿意
Mao brought this for you.
这是阿茂给你带的
It's black iridescent ore.
是乌彩矿
In her last letter, Yao Yao mentioned
上次夭夭来信说
that Yongzhou produces a rare kind of black iridescent ore
雍州出产一种很稀少的乌彩矿
that can forge the toughest black iron.
可以锻造出最坚硬的玄铁
Since I'm already there,
既然我都来了
I'll look for some on her behalf.
就替她找一找
It'll make an auspicious gift when I ask for her hand in marriage.
回去求亲也是个彩头
I only mentioned it once,
我只提了一次
and Mao went out of his way to find it for me.
阿茂便特意替我寻来了
Yao Yao,
夭夭
Mao has entered the palace.
阿茂他入宫了
He wants to ask the Empress Dowager
他想去求太后
to revoke the imperial marriage decree.
收回赐婚的旨意
I knew it.
我就知道
Mao would never give up.
阿茂一定不会放弃的
You want me to revoke the imperial marriage decree?
你想让吾收回赐婚旨意
I humbly ask that Your Majesty grant us your blessing.
恳请太后成全
Young men are naturally drawn to beauty.
知慕少艾
I understand that.
吾能理解
But
但
the decree has already been issued.
圣旨已下
I beg Your Majesty for mercy.
太后慈悲
In this life, I ask for nothing else
臣此生别无他求
but Lady Xie alone.
唯求谢娘子一人
You ask for nothing else?
别无他求
Your Majesty once promised
太后曾许诺过臣
that if I could find a miraculous doctor for His Majesty,
只要臣为陛下寻到神医
you would grant me another fiefdom.
便为臣开拓另一块封地
After enduring countless hardships,
臣历经艰险
I finally succeeded.
终于做到了
But now, I can forgo
可如今封地 爵位 财富
the land, the title, and the wealth.
臣都可以不要
I ask only that Your Majesty take pity on my sincere feelings.
请太后只怜臣的一片真心
You can give up
封地
your land,
爵位
your title,
财富
and your wealth?
都可以不要
It seems
看来是
I've played the part of a gentle and virtuous woman
吾这温良妇人演得久了
for so long that some fools have actually started to believe it.
久到还真有傻子信了
My son sits upon the throne,
我儿在御座之上
yet even he struggles just to survive,
尚且艰难求存
living like a puppet.
活得像个傀儡
And what are you?
你算个什么东西
What is your sincerity worth?
你的真心又算个什么东西
How dare you come here and bargain with me?
敢来跟吾谈条件
Everything you have now
你如今拥有的一切
was bestowed upon you by His Majesty and me.
都是吾和陛下赏你的
If I decide not to give it,
吾若不想给
then you shall have nothing.
便可以不给
He Tian!
贺田
Your servant awaits.
奴才在
Prince Qi trespassed into the inner palace
岐王擅闯宫禁
and spoke insolently to the Empress Dowager.
顶撞太后
Punish him with the rod!
杖
Da.
阿大
It's nothing. What happened?
没事 怎么了
Lejun?
乐君
Fainted?
晕过去了
Princess.
郡主
As soon as Lejun passed out,
乐君一昏过去
her maids came straight to the Grand Tutor's residence to fetch me.
婢女们就到太傅府来请我了
What happened to her?
她怎么了
Don't tell me her old illness has flared up again?
该不会是旧疾复发了
She'll be fine.
她没事的
She's fine?
没事
What,
怎么
Your Highness doesn't believe me?
殿下不信
I wouldn't dare.
李茂不敢
Your Highness is highly skilled in medicine,
郡主殿下精通医术
and it was you who cured Lejun's chronic illness before.
乐君的旧疾也是郡主治好的
However,
只不过
if she is truly fine,
若是真的没事的话
then why did she suddenly faint?
那又怎么会昏倒呢
She merely ate some wild fruit by mistake.
她是误食了野果而已
She'll recover naturally in a few days.
过几日自然就会好
However...
不过
something about this is strange.
不过此事蹊跷
To fall unconscious
误食野果
from eating that fruit,
若致昏迷
one would have to eat at least an entire basketful.
起码得吃够一筐才行
The fruit is sour and bitter—
此果味道酸涩
difficult to swallow.
难以入口
Why would Lejun eat so much of it?
乐君又怎会吃这么多
Go check whether the medicine is ready yet.
去看看药熬好了没
Yes.
诺
I'll go check on the medicine as well.
我也去看看药
Yao Yao.
夭夭
Mao.
阿茂
My mother wouldn't let me leave the residence,
阿母不让我出府
and I wanted to see you.
我想见你
Lejun said she had a way—
乐君说她有方法
I didn't expect this to be what she meant.
没想到竟然是这个
Are you alright?
你没事吧
Mao, you're finally back.
阿茂 你终于回来了
I thought
我还以为
I was really going to end up marrying someone else.
我真的要嫁给别人了
The Empress Dowager
太后她
still refuses to withdraw the decree.
还是不肯收回成命
Then I won't marry him either.
那我也不嫁
You're going to defy the imperial decree?
你要抗旨
Mao,
阿茂
I dare to defy the decree.
我敢抗旨
Do you dare?
你敢吗
Why wouldn't I dare?
为何不敢
Father always says I know nothing about court politics.
阿父总说我不懂朝政
Maybe he's right.
别的我是不懂
But I do know
但我知阿父
he has no intention of siding with Prince Jingan.
并不想投靠靖安王府
And besides, the Empress Dowager only ordered me to marry Xiao Wuyi.
而且太后只说让我嫁给萧无衣
She never said I had to spend my life in loving harmony with him.
又没说让我跟萧无衣恩爱白首
So as long as I complete the ceremony on the wedding night
所以我只要在大婚之夜
and run away afterward,
行完礼之后再逃跑
it won't count
到那时
as defying the decree.
我就不算抗旨了
I plan to go to Northern Qin,
我呢 打算去北秦
change my name,
隐姓埋名
and start over.
重新开始
Alright.
好啊
Yao Yao,
夭夭
no matter how powerful the Emperor and the Empress Dowager are,
陛下 太后的手再长
there's no way they can reach into Northern Qin to arrest anyone.
也绝对不可能伸到北秦去抓人的
It's just that
只是
the road ahead will be fraught with danger—
这一路势必危险重重
you must think this through carefully.
你一定要想好了
To be honest,
说实话
I am a little afraid.
我是有一些怕
The world outside
这外面的世界
is full of killing,
到处都是杀戮
deceit, and betrayal.
欺骗 背叛
But I can't let fear condemn me
可是我也不能因为害怕
to spending the rest of my life
就在靖安王府
trapped in Jingan Mansion.
葬送我的下半辈子
Yao Yao,
夭夭
no matter how disastrous this may become,
再泼天的大祸
if you want to go through with it,
只要你想闯
I'll be with you every step of the way.
我都陪你
What about Lejun?
那还有乐君妹妹呢
What will happen to her?
她怎么办
Of course she's coming with us.
自然和我们一起啊
Don't worry—
你放心
she likes you
她喜欢你
far more than she likes me, her own brother.
可远远超过我这个哥哥
Besides,
而且我们当时
back when we were fleeing for our lives,
逃难的时候就说了
we already promised that we'd face life and death together.
这辈子生死都在一起
Wait here a moment.
你等我一下啊
What's this?
这是
This...
这个呢
can be our token of promise.
就算是我们相约的信物了
I didn't expect things would still be
没想到大婚当前
so lively and carefree at Wuyi's place with the wedding so close at hand.
无衣这里依旧歌舞升平
Is this for your cousin?
送给你表哥的
Don't touch it.
别碰
Mao, coming by this late at night...
阿茂啊 这么晚来
you must have something important to say.
想必是有很重要的事要说吧
I assume you've already guessed it.
想必你已经猜到了
Lady Xie is the woman I love.
谢娘子是我的心上人
Is that all?
只是如此
She loves me too.
她也心悦于我
A gifted man and a beautiful woman—
郎才女貌
you are indeed well matched.
确实般配
I hope you will call off this engagement.
我希望你能退了这桩婚约
And if I refuse?
可若我不愿呢
You pressured the Empress Dowager into issuing the marriage decree
你逼太后下旨赐婚
for no reason other than to disrupt Prince Changsha's plans.
无非是为了搅乱长沙王的图谋
But Xie Jiayu is a person.
可谢嘉鱼是个人哪
She has feelings
她有自己的情感
and a life of her own.
自己的人生
She shouldn't have to
而她的人生
become an innocent sacrifice to your schemes.
不该为你的筹谋无辜牺牲
Mao,
阿茂
there are no innocent people in this world.
这世上没有无辜之人
The other day, Master asked me
那日老师还问我
whether, in my eyes,
在我心中
Xiao Wuyi was still a gentleman.
萧无衣是否为君子
Of course I'm not.
我自然不是
Nor do I want to be.
我也不想是
In an age of chaos,
大乱之世
gentlemen either fade into obscurity
君子或是落寞无闻
or die with their ambitions buried in the dust.
或是折戟沉沙
I will be
而我要做的
the one who holds the blade.
是执刀之人
Xiao Wuyi...
萧无衣
are you still the same young man
你还是当年那个
who once saved me from danger?
救我于水火的少年吗
This alliance cannot be called off.
这场联姻不能停
The wedding must proceed as scheduled.
大婚必须如约进行
Fine.
行
On the wedding day,
大婚当日
Xie Jiayu and I will leave together.
我会和谢嘉鱼一起走
Where could you possibly go?
你能去哪儿
To the ends of the earth.
天涯海角
Anywhere.
哪儿都行
Then you shouldn't have told me.
那你就不该告诉我
I'm telling you because I still consider you a friend.
那是因为我视你为友
If you want to stop me,
你若想拦
then just do it.
那便拦吧
You're just as naïve as she is.
你倒是和她一样天真
Mao actually managed to bring this back.
阿茂竟然真的把这个弄过来了
With this,
有了它
we won't get lost when we run away on the wedding day.
大婚的时候就不怕跑迷路了
Mother...
阿母
you already
其实
knew all along, didn't you?
您都知道了吧
Mother,
阿母
thank you.
谢谢您
What are you bowing for out of nowhere?
没头没脑 磕什么头
I know
我知道
that the last time
上次
I had Lejun eat those wild berries to get you to come,
我让乐君吃野果子请您来看
you had already noticed
您其实
I was hiding among the maids.
早就发现了我藏在婢女之中
You just chose not to expose me.
只是没有揭穿我
Later, you even went along with it
后来还顺水推舟
and took me to Prince Qi's residence.
带我去了岐王府
And these past few days, there's no way you wouldn't
这几日我在府里自己捣鼓
have noticed everything I've been secretly preparing in the residence.
您也不可能不知道
You simply turned a blind eye
您只是睁一只眼闭一只眼
because you intended to let me leave.
有意放我离开
Mother,
阿母
I have failed you.
女儿不孝
I've always upset you ever since I was young,
从前就总是惹您生气
and now I'm forcing you to make such a difficult choice.
现在还要让您做为难的决定
You're wrong.
你错了
The daughter I want
我想要的女儿
is not some puppet who only knows how to obey me,
并不是一个只会听我话的木偶
but a young woman
而是一个
who truly knows what she wants
真的知道自己想要什么
and what she ought to do.
知道自己该做什么的女郎
You've been through quite a bit by now.
你也算经历了一些事
You should understand that the world outside and the Grand Tutor's residence
应该知道外面与太傅府
are two entirely different worlds.
是两个世界
Now that you know how cruel the outside world can be,
知道了外面的残酷
you still intend to leave?
但你还是决定要走
I do.
要走
Then go.
那你就去
But remember this:
但记住
make absolutely sure you're fully prepared.
一定要做好万全的准备
Mother, don't worry.
阿母 您放心
Lejun and Mao will both be with me.
乐君和阿茂都会陪着我
Mao said
阿茂也说了
he'll take care of everything.
一切有他
No.
不
What I mean is
我说的是
that you yourself must also be fully prepared.
你自己也要做好万全的准备
Remember this:
记住
no matter when,
无论何时
the one you can truly rely on
你真正能依靠的
is never your parents,
不是父母
your husband,
夫君
or your children.
子女
It is yourself.
而是你自己
Over here, over here! Hurry up.
这边这边 快啊
Make sure you wipe it properly.
再擦仔细点
Alright!
好嘞
Xiao Wuyi did indeed risk returning to the capital.
萧无衣的确是冒险回京
There are at most 100 household guards inside Jingan Mansion,
靖安王府内最多一百部曲
and everything outside the city remains normal as well.
城外也一切如常
The Beifu Army is still stationed at the border.
北府大军仍在边关
As for the border garrison— he wouldn't dare make any rash move.
边关守军 他不敢轻举妄动
A bride-stealing?
抢婚
It's nothing more than an attempt
无非是想阻挠
to stop me from securing the support of the noble clans.
本王获得世家支持
The Beifu Army suffered heavy losses at Jiuzhang Plain.
九丈原北府损失惨重
We must not wait for the border forces to regroup before we act.
绝不能等边关休整好了再起事
Father.
阿父
Mother.
阿母
♪ You appear, but I can't hold you so ♪
我为您准备了一件礼物
It's for massaging your shoulders.
这是用来捶肩的
Look,
您看
Just like this.
就像这样
I understand
阿父明白
this is your way of showing filial devotion.
这是夭夭的一片孝心
My dear Yao Yao...
我的夭夭今天
you look so beautiful today.
今天好美啊
Father,
阿父
if I am no longer by your side in the future,
若日后女儿不在
you must take good care of yourself.
您一定要保重好身体
Silly child,
傻孩子
why are you crying?
你哭什么呢
I am not crying either.
阿父也没哭
We'll see each other again someday,
反正日后我们会再见嘛
won't we?
对不对
It's my fault
是阿父对不起你
for letting you be burdened by the Xie family.
让你受到了谢家的拖累
If you hadn't been my daughter,
如果你不是我的女儿
your life
你这辈子
would have been far freer.
会活得自在些
Please don't say that, Father.
阿父莫要这样说
Being born your daughter
能成为谢家的女儿
has made me very happy.
我很幸福
Mother.
阿母
The auspicious hour has arrived.
吉时已到
Young Master Xiao,
萧世子
it's been a long time.
好久不见
When have I ever met you?
我什么时候见过你
Fine.
行
It doesn't matter if you don't remember me.
你不记得我也无妨
After tonight,
今夜之后
I'll make sure you remember me deeply,
我定叫你印象深刻
for the rest of your life.
今生难忘
I look forward to it.
拭目以待
Alright, alright.
好了好了
Don't say things like that in public.
这种话别当众说啊
Off you go now—
你们快走吧
don't miss the auspicious hour.
莫耽误了吉时
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
a daughter of the Xie family is not so easily won.
我谢氏之女可不是这么好娶的
You—get down here.
你 下来
It's not straight.
歪了
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
萧无衣 你放开我
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
let go of me!
你放开我
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
萧无衣 你放开我
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
let go!
放开我
Lord Li, Madam Li.
李大人 李夫人
-Congratulations.
恭喜恭喜
Mr. Zhang, please come in.
张兄 里边请
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
萧无衣 你放开我
You jerk! You villain!
你个混蛋 坏人
Put me down!
你放我下来
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
萧无衣 你放开我
Let go of me! Put me down!
放开我 放我下来
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
put me down!
放我下来
Xiao Wuyi, put me down.
萧无衣 你放下
Xiao Wuyi, you...
萧无衣 你
Yan Yue.
偃月
-Yes. -Take her to the bridal chamber.
在 把她带进洞房
Don't give her any food
不准给她吃的
or water.
也不准给她喝的
Xiao Wuyi, just you wait.
萧无衣 你等着
Tonight, I'll make you regret this for the rest of your life.
今夜我让你后悔一辈子
Is this meant to be a show of force against the Xie family?
这是要给谢氏一个下马威吗
More than that.
何止谢氏
The one being humiliated is Grand Tutor Xie himself.
这羞辱的可是谢太傅
Take good care of my secondary consort.
好好照顾好你们的侧妃
I don't want to hear a single sound from her tonight.
今夜别让我再听到她的声音
Yes.
诺
Your Highness, the wedding rites haven't been completed yet.
世子 礼还没有成呢
Since you're all here,
既然都来了
drink with me tonight until we're completely drunk and no one leaves sober.
今夜就陪本世子喝个不醉不归
None of you are leaving.
一个都别想走
Wuyi,
二弟
tonight is the wedding bestowed by the Empress Dowager.
今夜是太后赐婚之夜
-Let's go. -Don't—
走 你别
Come on, let's drink!
喝酒
Your Highness,
殿下
most of the court officials invited to the wedding banquet have already arrived.
参加婚宴的朝臣已到大半
The remaining senior ministers are also on their way.
另几位重臣也已在路上
Proceed according to plan.
按计划行动
My life and death, my honor and disgrace— all depend on tonight.
本王的生死荣辱就在今夜
Yes.
诺
My Lady,
女郎
Xiao Wuyi is going too far.
萧无衣也太欺负人了
He actually had you carried all the way back to the mansion—
居然把咱们女郎一路架回王府
and on top of that…
还在
on your wedding night,
还在新婚之夜上
he's drinking and making merry with dancing girls.
与舞姬饮酒作乐
It doesn't matter.
没关系
In any case, the one who will be utterly humiliated tonight is him.
今夜丢大脸的反正是他
One at the door,
门口一个
and two outside the window.
窗外两个
Even the numbers line up exactly with the map.
连人数都跟地图上的对上了
Heaven is helping me!
真是天助我也
Are you all ready?
你们都准备好了吗
A top-grade sleeping draught.
顶级配方的蒙汗药
Is anyone outside?
外面有人吗
My Lady is in trouble—
我家女郎不好了
someone help!
快来人啊
Hurry! Come in, come in!
快进来 快进来
Let's go.
走
How come there isn't a single soul
这靖安王府
in this entire Jingan Mansion?
怎么连个人影都没有啊
Ugh… it stinks.
好臭
No, no—
不对 不对
this is the outhouse.
这边是茅房
The main gate is to the east...
院门向东
The kitchen's over there.
厨房在那边
Hurry, move!
快走快走
Don't block the entrance—
别堵在门口
we're serving food!
上菜呢
Douzi, take the slop out!
小豆子 把泔水倒出去
Alright!
好
Let's go.
走
What are you all doing here?
你们跑到这里来干什么
How was it?
怎么样
Did we seem real enough?
我们演得像真的吧
He was pretending too?
他也是装的
He wasn't.  You still need someone real in the mix, don't you?
他不是 总得有个真的呀
Your Highness, they've already left.
世子 人已经走了
Which route?
哪条路
As expected, the bride chose the back kitchen path.
新娘子选的果然是后厨
She just took several wrong turns along the way.
只不过中途走错了好几次
This is the hairpin she dropped.
这是她遗落的珠钗
Even with a map, she can't find her way.
给她地图跑都不会
She is so stupid.
真够笨的
It's bad—
不好了
the bride has escaped!
新娘子跑了
What did you say?
你说什么
In my mansion, from the guards to the gardeners,
我府中有府兵 园丁
groundskeepers, and stablehands—
花匠 马夫
every one of them knows martial arts.
无人不会武功
The moment she steps out of the courtyard gate,
只要她一出院门
she will be detected.
就会被发现
If you plan to escape,
若要跑
you would need my help.
除非我帮你们
This is the map of Jingan Mansion.
这是靖安王府的地图
Xie Jiayu will need it if she tries to escape the wedding.
谢嘉鱼逃婚时用得到
But this wedding must proceed as scheduled.
但这场大婚必须如约进行
because this is the day I have chosen for Prince Changsha
因为这是我为长沙王选的
to force the abdication.
逼宫之日
All guards of Jingan Mansion, heed my order.
靖安王府上下府兵听令
-Yes!
在
Search the entire city for Xie Jiayu!
全城搜捕谢嘉鱼
Yes, Your Highness.
诺
-Split up and search. -Make way.
分头搜 让开
-Move! -Make way!
让开 让开
What's going on?
出什么事了
Lady Xie has fled the wedding.
谢氏逃婚了
Xiao Wuyi has ordered his guards to search the entire city.
萧无衣正命府兵全城搜捕呢
This Lady Xie
这谢娘子
is always full of surprises.
总是出人意料啊
Your Highness, Jingan Mansion is now lightly guarded.
殿下 如今靖安王府内空虚
Should we strike immediately?
我们是不是现在立刻动手
A heaven-sent opportunity.
天赐良机
Issue the order inside and outside the capital—
传令京城内外
begin the uprising at once.
即刻起事
Yes.
诺
Attack!
上
Take Mother and leave, quickly!
快带母亲走
Yao, be careful!
尧儿 小心哪
Who are you?
什么人
How dare you act so recklessly in Jingan Mansion!
敢在靖安王府放肆
Yuanji!
元姬
Today,
今日
I shall cleanse His Majesty's side of traitors
本王要清君侧
and seize the rebels.
拿反贼
Among all the ministers in this courtyard,
这满院的大臣
which one is a rebel?
哪一个是反贼
Xiao Wuyi.
萧无衣
He brought troops back to the capital without imperial decree,
他无诏私自带兵回京
slaughtered court officials,
滥杀朝廷大臣
and harbors treasonous ambitions.
居心叵测
His crimes deserve death.
其罪当诛
Tonight,
今夜
who among you dare stand as his accomplice?
谁是他的同党
It seems
看来
the only rebel here is Xiao Wuyi himself.
就只有萧无衣一个反贼了
Your Highness, we've just received word—
殿下 刚刚传来消息
the palace gates have been breached.
宫门已破
Surround Jingan Mansion.
围住靖安王府
With Xiao Wuyi's family
萧无衣的家眷
and these court officials
还有这些朝臣
here,
他们在
he won't be able to escape.
萧无衣就跑不了了
The rest of you follow me into the palace
剩下的人随我入宫
to meet the Empress Dowager.
参见太后
Yes.
诺
Hurry! Move!
快快快
Search thoroughly—
都搜仔细了
leave no alley unchecked.
每条暗巷都别放过
Yes.
诺
Search!
搜
Your Highness,
世子
Xie Jiayu's trail has been found at Wuling Gate.
在武灵门发现谢嘉鱼行踪
Guard the city gate.
守住城门
I want her dead,
只要死的
not alive.
不要活的
Yes.
诺 诺 诺
Oh, Xiao Wuyi...
萧无衣啊 萧无衣
You're certainly ruthless—
狠倒是挺狠
but your eyesight isn't all that great.
就是眼神不太好
My Lady, it's just that you're blessed by the True Deity.
是女郎有真神庇佑
Even the heavens can't stand by
老天爷都看不下去
and have chosen to help you.
想帮您呢
Let's go quickly,
我们快走吧
or Mao will be getting anxious.
要不阿茂该等着急了
Let's go.
走走走
Master?
老师
His Majesty is gravely ill
陛下病重
and has summoned Prince Qi to enter the palace at once and attend upon him.
命岐王即刻入宫侍疾
I can't go to the palace.
我不能入宫
I need to find Yao Yao.
我要去找夭夭
Guards, escort Prince Qi to the palace.
来人 送岐王入宫
Lejun!
乐君
Brother!
阿兄
Your Highness.
殿下
Are all our men assembled?
人都到齐了吗
Tonight, we suddenly lost all contact
今夜我们突然失去了
with forces outside the capital.
跟京外的联系
Several units have been sent out, but none have reported back.
派出几路人马都不见回音
Lost contact?
失去联络
We won't wait any longer!
不等了
Victory or defeat, honor or disgrace— it all comes down to tonight.
成败荣辱就在今夜
Enter the palace now. Kill the Emperor and Empress Dowager!
入宫 杀了皇帝 太后
Yes!
诺
-Kill!
杀 杀 杀
Your Highness,
殿下
His Majesty is not in the main hall.
陛下不在殿内
Not there?
不在
That sickly man can't even get out of bed—
这病秧子床都下不了
where could he possibly go?
还能去哪儿
Find him!
给我找
Yes.
诺
Tell me—
说
where have you hidden that sickly emperor?
把那个病秧子藏哪儿了
My son is the true Son of Heaven.
我儿是真命天子
He is protected by the True Deity.
自有真神庇佑
You think you can find him so easily?
岂会让你找到
Don't think I'm unaware.
别以为我不知道
Had you not forged the imperial edict
当年要不是你伪造圣旨
and poisoned the late emperor,
毒死先帝
your son would never have become emperor.
轮得着你儿子当皇帝
But Heaven sees all.
不过好在老天有眼
Ever since he ascended the throne,
自从他当了皇帝
he's been bedridden with illness.
就一病不起
This is his retribution.
这就是报应
How insolent!
放肆
Utter nonsense!
一派胡言
My son is the true Son of Heaven!
我儿乃真命天子
Then let's see tonight
那就看看今天晚上
who truly holds Heaven's Mandate.
天命站在谁那边
Guards—
给我
Why didn't you attend my wedding tonight?
今夜怎么不来喝我的喜酒啊
Xiao Wuyi, didn't you go find Xie...
萧无衣 你不是去找谢
It doesn't matter.
无妨
Tonight, my 20,000 troops have already taken control of the capital.
今夜我两万部曲已经控制京城
Those who follow me will prosper; those who oppose me will perish.
顺我者昌 逆我者亡
Kill Xiao Wuyi!
杀了萧无衣
What are you afraid of?
怕什么
Whoever kills Xiao Wuyi shall be granted a fief of ten thousand households!
杀萧无衣者 赏万户
You mean those forces outside the capital?
你是说城外的那些
I've already wiped them out.
被我杀了
What do you mean?
什么意思
Kneel!
跪下
-Spare us, Your Highness! -Please spare us!
世子饶命啊 世子
Where are they?
人呢
Where are the others?
其他人呢
-Please spare us, Your Highness! -Please spare us!
世子饶命 世子饶命 世子饶命
No… I won't lose.
不 我不会输
I absolutely will not lose.
绝不会输
I still have Jingan Mansion,
我手里还有靖安王府
all those ministers,
还有那么多王公大臣
and your entire family.  If you dare—
还有你一家老小 你要是敢
His Highness has given the order—
王爷传令
kill!
杀
Yes.
诺
Who dares take another step forward?
谁敢上前
I am the Princess of Jingan Mansion,
我乃靖安王府世子妃
the Empress Dowager's own niece.
当今太后的亲侄女
Let's see who dares lay a hand on me today!
我看今天谁敢动我
Did you think I didn't know
你以为我不知道
you would move against Jingan Mansion?
你会对靖安王府下手吗
How dare a useless drunkard from pleasure-filled Jiankang City like you
剑慷城温柔乡里的酒囊饭袋
play war games with me?
竟敢同我玩兵法
Father.
父王
Are you alright?
还行
I'm fine.
无碍
Your Highness.
王爷
My Lady.
夫人
Lady Rui, have you not been in the mansion these past few days?
蕊夫人 你这几日一直不在府中
Due to urgent military matters,
军情紧急
Wuyi asked her to guide me outside the capital.
无衣让她到城外给我带路
Yao.
尧儿
It's alright.
不要紧
All of you, listen well!
尔等听着
Prince Changsha has attempted a palace coup.
长沙王逼宫谋逆
The Beifu Army has marched thousands of miles to suppress the rebellion.
我北府将士千里平叛
At this very moment,
此时此刻
my son Xiao Wuyi has already captured Prince Changsha alive within the palace.
我儿萧无衣已在宫中生擒长沙王
Surrender immediately!
尔等 即刻投降
or you will all be slain without mercy.
否则 杀无赦
The Beifu Army is back…
北府军回来了
Is this truly suppressing a rebellion… or starting one?
这是平叛还是造反哪
I can't accept this!
不甘心哪
I'm unwilling to keep being trampled
不甘心被这个废物皇帝
under the feet of that useless emperor.
一直踩在脚底下
Do you regret it?
后悔吗
Regret?
后悔
I have never felt so alive and satisfied.
我从来没有像今夜这么痛快过
Xiao Wuyi, do you think killing me
萧无衣 你以为杀了我
will avenge the Beifu Army who died in vain?
就能为枉死的北府军报仇
Don't think you're any different from me—
别以为你跟我不一样
don't you also want to kill that useless emperor
不想杀了这个废物皇帝
and take his place in this Xianyang Hall?
自己住进这座显阳殿
Aunt…
叔母
Your Majesty…
太后
Xiao Wuyi will kill you both sooner or later.
萧无衣一定会杀了你们的
Perhaps even tonight.
或许就在今夜
How foolish and self-deceived.
蠢不自知啊
You don't even know who is the piece
就连今夜谁是棋子
and who is the player on this board.
谁是棋手都不知道
I originally believed Prince Changsha
我原本以为是长沙王
had secretly colluded with Wonderful Master,
暗通妙手公子
bribing the Armory Director in my army
买通我军中武库令
to purchase a batch of defective repeating crossbows.
将一批劣质连弩购入军中
But it turned out Wonderful Master
结果发现妙手公子
didn't even know you.
根本就不认识你
The real mastermind behind the purchase
其实真正的幕后买家
is the Empress Dowager.
是太后
The one who most wants to see me and Prince Changsha destroy each other…
最希望我和长沙王不死不休的人
is also the Empress Dowager.
也是太后
Young Master Xiao, you are indeed perceptive.
萧世子聪慧
The official in charge of military supplies, Treasurer Wei,
管理军械的魏少府
is an ally of Prince Changsha.
是长沙王的党附
As long as you handed him the design plans,
太后只要将设计图交给魏少府
he would complete the rest of the scheme with Prince Changsha,
他便会和长沙王完成剩下的事
and eliminate both me and the Beifu Army.
置臣和北府军于死地
Just like tonight—
就像今夜
Your Majesty neither mobilized troops nor prepared defenses,
太后不调兵 不防备
betting that even though I knew this palace entry was a trap,
不正是赌我明知无诏入宫是陷阱
I would still refuse to let Prince Changsha succeed.
也绝不会让长沙王成功吗
So tonight,
所以
Your Majesty's target
太后今夜的目标
is not only Prince Changsha…
不仅是长沙王
but me as well.
也是臣
What a perfect invitation into a trap.
好一招请君入瓮
I always thought
一直以为
you were nothing more than a useless old woman.
你就是个一无是处的老妇
I didn't expect this.
没想到
Fine—
行
I lose this round
这局
without complaint.
输得不冤
Since you already knew tonight was a trap,
你早知今日是陷阱
why did you still come?
又何必入宫来
Because I did not want
因为我不想让
Jiankang to run red with blood tonight.
今夜的剑慷血流成河
But
但
I must demand justice for the 30,000 fallen soldiers
我要为枉死的北府三万将士
of the Beifu Army.
讨个公道
Brave indeed.
好胆识
I can spare your life.
吾可以饶你不死
If you are willing to surrender your military command,
若你肯交出兵权
I will grant you immunity.
吾恕你无罪
And if I refuse?
如果我说不呢
Empress Dowager,
太后
I submitted the roster of our fallen soldiers
臣将阵亡将士名单呈上
half a month ago.
已有半月
I wonder if you have read it?
不知太后可否看过了
Not yet.
尚未
Shi Yuchun,
史喻春
46 years old—
四十六岁
stabbed over 100 times, yet died without kneeling.
身中百余刀死而不跪
Xie Han, a veteran of the Beifu Army.
谢函 北府老兵
He spent his entire life at war,
打了一辈子仗
and could have laid down his armor and returned home—
原本可以卸甲归田
but his homeland had already fallen to Northern Qin.
但他的故乡却早已沦为北秦土地
He said he has nowhere else to go
他说他无家可归
and wishes to spend the rest of his life in the army.
想要老死在军中
This time,
这一次
he truly did die—
他的确死了
his body trampled into a pulp beneath enemy hooves.
尸骨被敌军踏成肉泥
Zhang Ji, my most trusted deputy.
张寂 我最好的副将
He personally set fire to the vine-armored grain depot
他亲手点燃藤甲粮仓
and perished together with the enemy.
最终与敌军同归于尽
Does Your Majesty know any of this?
这些太后知道吗
Do you, sitting here in Jiankang, even care?
身在剑慷的你 在乎过吗
That is why I will not surrender my command—
所以我不会交出兵权
because apart from me,
因为除了我
no one else cares about their lives.
没人在乎他们的命
Xiao Wuyi,
萧无衣
the Beifu Army entered the capital without an imperial decree.
北府兵无诏进京
Are you trying to rebel?
你是想造反吗
But you will end up returning to Jiankang without the Emperor's decree.
可你回剑慷没有陛下旨意
What about mobilizing troops?
那调兵呢
Prince Changsha seeks rebellion—
长沙王想要谋反
what about you?
那你呢
Your Majesty,
太后
all I want is peace across the realm.
我想要的只是天下太平
Is Your Majesty willing to grant that?
太后肯给吗
Have you ever heard the war drums
太后可曾听过
of the Beifu Army?
北府军的战鼓声
One hundred thousand Beifu troops
十万北府兵
are just outside the city now.
就在城外